This is an image of the planet Earth.
هذه صورة لكوكب الأرض
It looks very much like the Apollo pictures
إنها تبدو شديدة الشبه بلوحات أبولو
that are very well known.
المعروفة جيدا
There is something different;
هناك شيء مختلف
you can click on it,
تستطيع ان تضغظ عليها
and if you click on it,
ولو ضغطت عليها
you can zoom in on almost any place on the Earth.
تستطيع التقريب علي اي نقطة تريدها علي الارض
For instance, this is a bird's-eye view
بالنسبة إينستانكسي، هذا منظر بديعا
of the EPFL campus.
في الحرم الجامعي في لوزان.
In many cases, you can also see
في كثير من الحالات، يمكنك أن ترى أيضا
how a building looks from a nearby street.
كيف يبدو مبنى من شارع مجاور.
This is pretty amazing.
وهذا مدهشا.
But there's something missing in this wonderful tour:
لكن هناك شيء مفقود في هذه الجولة الرائعة:
It's time.
لقد حان الوقت.
i'm not really sure when this picture was taken.
لست متأكداً حقاً متي ألتقطت هذه الصورة.
I'm not even sure it was taken
أنا لست متأكداً حتى أنها التقطت
at the same moment as the bird's-eye view.
في نفس اللحظة كمنظر كاشفا من أعلي
In my lab, we develop tools
في مختبري، نقوم بتطوير أدوات
to travel not only in space
للسفر ليس فقط في الفضاء
but also through time.
ولكن أيضا من خلال الوقت.
The kind of question we're asking is
نوع السؤال الذي نسأله هو
Is it possible to build something
هل من الممكن بناء شيء
like Google Maps of the past?
مثل "خرائط جوجل" من الماضي؟
Can I add a slider on top of Google Maps
يمكن إضافة شريط تمرير على رأس "خرائط جوجل"
and just change the year,
وبمجرد تغيير السنة،
seeing how it was 100 years before,
يمكننا رؤية كيف كانت منذ 100 سنة
1,000 years before?
منذ 1000 سنة ؟
Is that possible?
هل هذا ممكن؟
Can I reconstruct social networks of the past?
هل يمكنني إعادة بناء الشبكات الاجتماعية من الماضي؟
Can I make a Facebook of the Middle Ages?
هل بإمكاني صنع فيس بوك من العصور الوسطى؟
So, can I build time machines?
اذا، هل يمكنني بناء آلات الوقت؟
Maybe we can just say, "No, it's not possible."
ربما يمكننا أن نقول، "لا ليست ممكنة."
Or, maybe, we can think of it from an information point of view.
أو، ربما، يمكن أن نفكر في أنه من وجهة نظر معلوماتية.
This is what I call the information mushroom.
وهذا ما نسميه فطر المعلومات.
Vertically, you have the time.
عمودياً، لديك الوقت.
and horizontally, the amount of digital information available.
وأفقيا، كمية المعلومات الرقمية المتاحة.
Obviously, in the last 10 years, we have much information.
ومن الواضح، أننا في السنوات العشر الماضية، لدينا الكثير من المعلومات.
And obviously the more we go in the past, the less information we have.
ومن الواضح أنه كلما ذهبنا للماضي، قلّت المعلومات لدينا.
If we want to build something like Google Maps of the past,
إذا كنا نريد بناء شيء مثل "خرائط جوجل" من الماضي،
or Facebook of the past,
أو فيس بوك الماضي،
we need to enlarge this space,
نحتاج إلى توسيع هذه المساحة،
we need to make that like a rectangle.
نحن بحاجة إلى جعلها كمستطيل.
How do we do that?
كيف نفعل ذلك؟
One way is digitization.
طريقة واحدة هي الرقمنة.
There's a lot of material available --
وهناك الكثير من المواد المتاحة-
newspaper, printed books, thousands of printed books.
صحيفة، الكتب المطبوعة، آلاف الكتب المطبوعة.
I can digitize all these.
يمكنني رقمنة كل هذا
I can extract information from these.
يمكنني استخراج المعلومات من هذه.
Of course, the more you go in the past, the less information you will have.
وبطبيعة الحال، كلما ذهبت للماضي، قلّت المعلومات لديك
So, it might not be enough.
لذا، قد لا يكون كافياً.
So, I can do what historians do.
لذلك، يمكنني أن أفعل ما فعله المؤرخون.
I can extrapolate.
يمكنني الاستقراء.
This is what we call, in computer science, simulation.
وهذا ما نسميه، في علوم الكمبيوتر ب &amp;quot;المحاكاة&amp;quot;.
If I take a log book,
إذا أخذت سجل دفتري،
I can consider, it's not just a log book
يمكني اعتباره ليس مجرد سجل
of a Venetian captain going to a particular journey.
لكابتن من البندقية ذاهب لرحلة معينة.
I can consider it is actually a log book
يمكنني اعتباره حقيقة سجل
which is representative of many journeys of that period.
ممثلا للعديد من الرحلات في تلك الفترة.
I'm extrapolating.
وأنا أبالغ في الاستقراء.
If I have a painting of a facade,
فإذا كان لدى لوحة واجهة،
I can consider it's not just that particular building,
يمكنني اعتبره ليس فقط بناءا خاصا،
but probably it also shares the same grammar
ولكن ربما يشارك نفس قواعد
of buildings where we lost any information.
الابنية حيث فقدنا كل المعلومات
So if we want to construct a time machine,
فإذا كنا نريد بناء آلة الزمن،
we need two things.
فنحن بحاجة إلى أمرين اثنين.
We need very large archives,
نحن بحاجة إلى أرشيف ضخم للغاية
and we need excellent specialists.
و بحاجة إلى متخصصين جيدين
The Venice Time Machine,
آلة زمن البندقية،
the project I'm going to talk to you about,
المشروع الذي سأخبركم عنه
is a joint project between the EPFL
مشروع مشترك بين لوزان
and the University of Venice Ca'Foscari.
وجامعة البندقية.
There's something very peculiar about Venice,
هناك شيء غريب جداً عن البندقية،
that its administration has been
أن إدارته لديها
very, very bureaucratic.
بيروقراطية سيئة جداً.
They've been keeping track of everything,
فلقد تم حفظ مسار كل شيء،
almost like Google today.
تقريبا مثل جوجل اليوم.
At the Archivio di Stato,
في محفوظات دي ساتو،
you have 80 kilometers of archives
لديك على بعد 80 كيلومترا من المحفوظات
documenting every aspect
توثيق كل جوانب
of the life of Venice over more than 1,000 years.
الحياة في البندقية على مدى أكثر من ألف سنة.
You have every boat that goes out,
لديك توثيق لكل قارب يخرج،
every boat that comes in.
وكل قارب يدخل
You have every change that was made in the city.
لديك كل تغيير تم إجراؤه في المدينة.
This is all there.
وهذا كل شيء هناك.
We are setting up a 10-year digitization program
ونحن بإعداد برنامج رقمنة 10 سنوات
which has the objective of transforming
حيث يهدف الي تحويل
this immense archive
هذا الأرشيف الهائل
into a giant information system.
الي نظام معلومات عملاق.
The type of objective we want to reach
نوع الهدف الذي نريد التوصل إليه
is 450 books a day that can be digitized.
هو رقمنة 450 كتاب يوميا
Of course, when you digitize, that's not enough,
وبطبيعة الحال، عندما ترقمن، فهذا لا يكفي،
because these documents,
نظراً لأن هذه الوثائق،
most of them are in Latin, in Tuscan,
معظمها في أمريكا اللاتينية، في توسكان،
in Venetian dialect,
في لهجة البندقية،
so you need to transcribe them,
لذا تحتاج إلى نسخ منها،
to translate them in some cases,
لترجمتهم في بعض الحالات،
to index them,
لوضعهم في مرجع
and this is obviously not easy.
ومن الواضح أن هذا ليس سهلاً.
In particular, traditional optical character recognition method
في أسلوب التعرف البصري على الحروف التقليدية وخاصة
that can be used for printed manuscripts,
التي يمكن استخدامها للمخطوطات المطبوعة،
they do not work well on the handwritten document.
أنها لا تعمل جيدا في وثيقة مكتوبة بخط اليد.
So the solution is actually to take inspiration
لذا الحل في الواقع هو الإلهام
from another domain: speech recognition.
بطريقة آخري: التعرف على الكلام.
This is a domain of something that seems impossible,
وهذا هو مجال الشيء الذي يبدو مستحيلاً،
which can actually be done,
وما يمكن فعله حقيقة
simply by putting additional constraints.
ببساطة عن طريق وضع قيود إضافية.
If you have a very good model
إذا كان لديك نموذج جيد جداً
of a language which is used,
من اللغة التي يتم استخدامها،
if you have a very good model of a document,
إذا كان لديك نموذج جيد جداً لمستند،
how well they are structured.
كيف أنها منظمة بشكل جيد.
And these are administrative documents.
وهذه هي الوثائق الإدارية.
They are well structured in many cases.
منظمة بشكل جيد في كثير من الحالات.
If you divide this huge archive into smaller subsets
إذا قمت بتقسيم هذا الأرشيف الضخم إلى مجموعات فرعية أصغر
where a smaller subset actually shares similar features,
حيث المجموعات الفرعية الأصغر تتشارك في ميزات مماثلة،
then there's a chance of success.
ثم أن هناك فرصة للنجاح.
If we reach that stage, then there's something else:
إذا وصلنا إلى هذه المرحلة، ثم هناك شيء آخر:
we can extract from this document events.
يمكن أن نستخلص من هذه المستند أحداث
Actually probably 10 billion events
في الواقع ربما 10 مليار حدث
can be extracted from this archive.
يمكن أن تستخلصها من هذا الأرشيف.
And this giant information system
وهذا النظام المعلوماتي العملاق
can be searched in many ways.
يمكن بحثه بالعديد من الطرق.
You can ask questions like,
يمكنك أن تطرح أسئلة مثل،
"Who lived in this palazzo in 1323?"
&amp;quot; من الذين عاشوا في هذا القصر في 1323&amp;quot;؟
"How much cost a sea bream at the Realto market
"كم تكلفة الشبوط في سوق ريالتو
in 1434?"
في 1434؟ "
"What was the salary
&amp;quot;ما كان راتب
of a glass maker in Murano
صانع الزجاج في مورانو
maybe over a decade?"
ربما من عقد ؟ &amp;quot;
You can ask even bigger questions
يمكنك طرح أسئلة حتى أكبر
because it will be semantically coded.
لأنها سوف تكون مشفرة لغوياً.
And then what you can do is put that in space,
ومن ثم ما يمكنك القيام به هو وضع ذلك في الفضاء،
because much of this information is spatial.
لأن الكثير من هذه المعلومات مكانية.
And from that, you can do things like
ومن ذلك، يمكنك القيام بأشياء مثل
reconstructing this extraordinary journey
إعادة إعمار هذه الرحلة الغير عادية
of that city that managed to have a sustainable development
لتلك المدينة التي تمكنت من التنمية المستدامة
over a thousand years,
علي مدار ألف سنة،
managing to have all the time
استطاعت في كل الاوقات ان تصنع
a form of equilibrium with its environment.
نموذج للتوازن مع بيئتها.
You can reconstruct that journey,
أنت يمكنك إعادة بناء تلك الرحلة،
visualize it in many different ways.
وتصورها بالعديد من الطرق المختلفة.
But of course, you cannot understand Venice if you just look at the city.
ولكن بطبيعة الحال، لا تستطيع أن تفهم مدينة البندقية بمجرد إلقاء نظرة على المدينة.
You have to put it in a larger European context.
يجب عليك ان تضعها في سياق أوروبي أكبر.
So the idea is also to document all the things
وبالتالي هناك فكرة لتوثيق جميع الأشياء ايضا
that worked at the European level.
التي عملت على الصعيد الأوروبي.
We can reconstruct also the journey
يمكنك ايضا إعادة بناء رحلة
of the Venetian maritime empire,
الإمبراطورية البحرية بمدينة البندقية،
how it progressively controlled the Adriatic Sea,
كيف أنها سيطرت تدريجيا علي البحر اﻷدرياتيكي،
how it became the most powerful medieval empire
كيف أصبحت أقوى إمبراطورية في العصور الوسطى
of its time,
وقتها،
controlling most of the sea routes
السيطرة على معظم الطرق البحرية
from the east to the south.
من الشرق إلى الجنوب.
But you can even do other things,
يمكنك أن تفعل أشياء أخرى ايضا،
because in these maritime routes,
لأن في هذه الطرق البحرية،
there are regular patterns.
هناك أنماط منتظمة.
You can go one step beyond
يمكن أن تذهب خطوة واحدة للخارج
and actually create a simulation system,
وتنشئ نظام للمحاكاة،
create a Mediterranean simulator
إنشاء جهاز محاكاة البحر الأبيض المتوسط
which is capable actually of reconstructing
وهو قادر على إعادة إعمار
even the information we are missing,
حتى المعلومات المفتقدة
which would enable us to have questions you could ask
التي سوف تمكننا من الحصول علي الأسئلة التي يمكن أن تسألها
like if you were using a route planner.
مثل إذا كنت تستخدم مخطط مسار.
"If I am in Corfu in June 1323
&amp;quot;إذا كنت في كورفو في يونيه 1323
and want to go to Constantinople,
وأريد أن اذهب إلى القسطنطينية،
where can I take a boat?"
أين يمكنني أن أجد قارب؟ &amp;quot;
Probably we can answer this question
ربما يمكننا الإجابة على هذا السؤال
with one or two or three days' precision.
خلال واحد أو اثنين أو بالدقة ثلاثة أيام.
"How much will it cost?"
&amp;quot;كم سوف يكلف؟&amp;quot;
"What are the chance of encountering pirates?"
"ما هي الفرصة لمواجهة القراصنة؟"
Of course, you understand,
بالطبع، أنت تفهم،
the central scientific challenge of a project like this one
التحدي العلمي المركزي لمشروع مثل هذا
is qualifying, quantifying and representing
التأهيل، التحديد الكمي، وهو ما يمثل
uncertainty and inconsistency at each step of this process.
عدم اليقين وعدم التناسق في كل خطوة من هذه العملية.
There are errors everywhere,
هناك أخطاء في كل مكان،
errors in the document, it's the wrong name of the captain,
أخطاء في المستند، وهو الاسم الخاطئ للقبطان،
some of the boats never actually took to sea.
وبعض القوارب لم تذهب ابدًا إلى البحر.
There are errors in translation, interpretative biases,
هناك أخطاء في الترجمة، والتحيزات التفسيرية،
and on top of that, if you add algorithmic processes,
وعلاوة على ذلك، إذا قمت بإضافة عمليات حسابية،
you're going to have errors in recognition,
ستواجه أخطاء في التعرّف على الانماط،
errors in extraction,
أخطاء في الاستخراج،
so you have very, very uncertain data.
وبالتالي لديك معلومات غير مؤكدة
So how can we detect and correct these inconsistencies?
فكيف يمكننا اكتشاف وتصحيح حالات عدم الاتساق هذه؟
How can we represent that form of uncertainty?
كيف يمكن أن تصور هذا الشكل من عدم اليقين؟
It's difficult. One thing you can do
أمر صعب. ولكن هناك شيء واحد يمكنك القيام به
is document each step of the process,
ان توثق كل خطوة من العملية،
not only coding the historical information
ليس فقط ترميز المعلومات التاريخية
but what we call the meta-historical information,
ولكن ما نسميه المعلومات الفوقية التاريخية،
how is historical knowledge constructed,
كيف شيدت المعرفة التاريخية
documenting each step.
توثيق كل خطوة.
That will not guarantee that we actually converge
والتي لن تضمن ان نتلاقي فعليا
toward a single story of Venice,
نحو قصة واحدة لمدينة البندقية،
but probably we can actually reconstruct
ولكن ربما نستطيع فعلا إعمار
a fully documented potential story of Venice.
قصة محتملة موثقة بالكامل عن مدينة البندقية
Maybe there's not a single map.
ربما لا يوجد خريطة واحدة.
Maybe there are several maps.
ربما هناك عدة خرائط.
The system should allow for that,
يجب أن يسمح النظام لذلك،
because we have to deal with a new form of uncertainty,
لأن علينا أن نتعامل مع نموذج جديد من عدم اليقين،
which is really new for this type of giant databases.
وهو حقاً جديداً لهذا النوع من قواعد البيانات العملاقة.
And how should we communicate
وكيف ينبغي أن نصنع تواصل
this new research to a large audience?
بين هذا البحث الجديد و الجمهور الكبير؟
Again, Venice is extraordinary for that.
مرة أخرى، البندقية استثنائية لذلك.
With the millions of visitors that come every year,
مع ملايين الزوار التي تأتي كل سنة،
it's actually one of the best places
هي في الواقع واحدة من أفضل الأماكن
to try to invent the museum of the future.
في محاولة لاختراع المتحف في المستقبل.
Imagine, horizontally you see the reconstructed map
تخيل، أفقياً انت تشاهد الخريطة التي أعيد بناؤها
of a given year,
في سنة معينة،
and vertically, you see the document
وعمودياً، انت ترى الوثيقة
that served the reconstruction,
التي خدمت إعادة الإعمار،
paintings, for instance.
لوحات، على سبيل المثال.
Imagine an immersive system that permits
تخيل نظام غمر يسمح
to go and dive and reconstruct the Venice of a given year,
للذهاب والغوص وإعادة بناء مدينة البندقية في سنة معينة،
some experience you could share within a group.
بعض الخبرة يمكن أن تتشارك فيها ضمن مجموعة.
On the contrary, imagine actually that you start
علي النقيض، تخيل في الواقع انك يمكنك البدء
from a document, a Venetian manuscript,
من مستند، مخطوطة للبندقية،
and you show, actually, what you can construct out of it,
ويمكنك إظهار، في الواقع، ما يمكنك أعادة إعماره منها،
how it is decoded,
كيف يتم فك الشفرة،
how the context of that document can be recreated.
كيف يمكن أن يعاد سياق تلك الوثيقة.
This is an image from an exhibit
هذه صورة من معرض
which is currently conducted in Geneva
المقام حاليا في جنيف
with that type of system.
مع هذا النوع من النظام.
So to conclude, we can say that
في الختام، يمكننا القول بأن
research in the humanities is about to undergo
البحوث في مجال العلوم الإنسانية على وشك الخضوع
an evolution which is maybe similar
لتطور الذي ربما يشبه
to what happened to life sciences 30 years ago.
ما حدث لعلوم الحياة منذ 30 عاماً.
It's really a question of scale.
أنها حقاً مسألة الحجم.
We see projects which are
ونحن نرى المشاريع التي
much beyond any single research team can do,
تفوق قدرة فريق بحث واحد لعملها
and this is really new for the humanities,
وهذا جديد للعلوم الإنسانية،
which very often take the habit of working
التي تأخذ في كثير من الأحيان عادة العمل
in small groups or only with a couple of researchers.
في مجموعات صغيرة، أو فقط مع اثنين من الباحثين.
When you visit the Archivio di Stato,
عند قيامك بزيارة محفوظات دي ساتو،
you feel this is beyond what any single team can do,
تشعر انه يفوق قدرة فريق عمل واحد
and that should be a joint and common effort.
وينبغي أن يكون جهدا مشتركاً
So what we must do for this paradigm shift
ولذا ما يجب أن نفعله لهذه النقلة النوعية
is actually foster a new generation
هو فعلا تعزيز جيل جديد
of "digital humanists"
من &amp;quot;الإنسانية الرقمية&amp;quot;
that are going to be ready for this shift.
التي ستكون جاهزة لهذا التحول.
I thank you very much.
أشكركم جزيل الشكر.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)